<?xml version="1.0"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
 
  <title>blog.chicagolobbyists.org</title>
  <link href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/"/>
  <link type="application/atom+xml" rel="self" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/atom.xml"/>
  <updated>2012-01-19T13:19:53-06:00</updated>
  <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Chicago Lobbyists Blog</name>
    <email>chi.lobbyists@gmail.com</email>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2012/01/12/chicago-aint-ready-for-procurement-reform</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2012/01/12/chicago-aint-ready-for-procurement-reform/"/>
    <title>Chicago ain’t ready for procurement reform - Despite changes, the city continues to shut out tech innovators</title>
    <updated>2012-01-12T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p class='r'&gt;&lt;a href='/docs/RFPdeclined.pdf'&gt;&lt;img src='/images/Proposal_Declined.png' alt='Proposal Declined' title='Proposal Declined' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan 12, 2012 – We recently received a &lt;a href='/docs/RFPdeclined.pdf'&gt;rejection letter&lt;/a&gt; from the City of Chicago regarding our &lt;a href='/2011/12/15/our-response-to-chicagos-lobbyist-rfp/'&gt;bid&lt;/a&gt; to build them an online lobbyist registration app. &lt;a href='http://www.crowehorwath.com/'&gt;Crowe Horwath &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;LLP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, an accounting and consulting firm based in Oak Brook, lllinois, won the bid instead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were almost certainly rejected because we did not fulfill the &lt;a href='/docs/Spec101998.pdf'&gt;application requirements&lt;/a&gt; set out by the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cityofchicago.org/city/en/depts/dps.html&quot;&gt;Department of Procurement Services&lt;/a&gt;. We never intended to. Despite being very competent technologists and experts on lobbying data, we simply couldn’t meet them: The city’s requirements are not crafted with tech startups in mind.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite Mayor Emanuel’s pledge to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cityofchicago.org/content/dam/city/depts/mayor/supp_info/chicago_2011_transition_report.pdf&quot;&gt;promote entrepreneurship&lt;/a&gt;, his moves to &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cityofchicago.org/city/en/depts/mayor/press_room/press_releases/2011/may_2011/Mayor_elect_Emanuel_Names_Chicagos_Technology_Leadership_Team.html&quot;&gt;modernize the city’s technology&lt;/a&gt;, and his promise that last year’s &lt;a href=&quot;http://blogs.wttw.com/moreonthestory/2011/07/21/mayor-emanuel-announces-reforms-in-city-contracting/&quot;&gt;city contracting reforms&lt;/a&gt; would “ensure competitive, accountable and open bidding,” high barriers to entry that protect entrenched incumbents and shut out innovative startups are still very much in place.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;“In private industry, many organizations have adapted their procurement process to suit modern website development,” says Paul Baker, the co-founder and president of Webitects, a web design firm. “The city still treats it like you’re pouring 60,000 tons of concrete, like you’re building a bridge.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Smart organizations judge you based on your track record and the quality of your (proposed) solutions to their problems. The city, on the other hand, focuses on requirements: of the 152-page &lt;a href='/docs/Spec101998.pdf'&gt;request for proposal&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt;) the city issued for the lobbyists app, only 10 pages touch on actual applications specs (p. 87 &amp;#8211; 97.) The rest is largely forms and legalese.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why? Because the city is more concerned with minimizing the risk of project failure than with seeking out ideas and ability. Though the intent is no doubt to protect taxpayers, the results are perverse: innovators are shut out, city IT is stuck in the stone age, city workers and citizens lose.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Consider the firm the city chose to build the lobbyist system: Crowe Horath is the same company that built the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.cityofchicago.org/city/en.html&quot;&gt;City of Chicago’s current website&lt;/a&gt;. The city paid them &lt;a href=&quot;http://newsblogs.chicagotribune.com/clout_st/2010/03/city-of-chicago-unveils-redesigned-web-site.html&quot;&gt;$1.8 million&lt;/a&gt; in 2010 to carry out the city’s first website redesign in 9 years. This company also built the &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.explorechicago.org/city/en.html&quot;&gt;Explore Chicago&lt;/a&gt; tourism website, and &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.crowehorwath.com/ContentDetails.aspx?id=1321&quot;&gt;applied the same design&lt;/a&gt; to the City of Chicago site.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At an &lt;a href='http://www.meetup.com/OpenGovChicago/events/38655692/'&gt;OpenGov Chicago meet up&lt;/a&gt; in November, the group discussed the City&amp;#8217;s website. Some people &lt;a href='https://groups.google.com/forum/embed/?place=forum/OpenGovChicago#!topic/opengovchicago/Zr284xOnARU'&gt;raised usability issues, and several suggestions for improvement were made&lt;/a&gt;. The city seems to recognize that there are issues with the site, since they are looking to redesign it again after being in use for less than two years. (&lt;em&gt;Note: I am a co-organizer of OpenGov Chicago, but this blog post is my own opinion and not a statement on behalf of the group&lt;/em&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The question now is, with Mayor Emanuel touting innovation and change, why is it still business as usual when it comes doling out taxpayer dollars for the projects that really matter?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We believe technology can help transform government at the core. But Government 2.0 will never become a reality without real procurement reform to level the playing field for innovative newcomers. In other words, &lt;a href=&quot;http://www.informationdiet.com/blog/read/procurement-is-americas-big-problem&quot;&gt;procurement is the problem&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And we want to be part of the solution. We’re announcing the creation of a nonprofit &lt;a href=&quot;http://radar.oreilly.com/2011/12/2011-gov2-year-in-review.html#civic-startups&quot;&gt;civic startup&lt;/a&gt;: an open gov, open-source development shop that will not just build apps on open data, but also compete to build re-usable software that transforms how government does business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More on this to come soon.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2012/01/06/outside-the-loop-interview</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2012/01/06/outside-the-loop-interview/"/>
    <title>Chicago Lobbyists team interview on Outside the Loop Radio</title>
    <updated>2012-01-06T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Derek Eder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class='r'&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.outsidetheloopradio.com/2012/01/05/otl-episode-276-chicagolobbyists-org-discussing-the-local-comedy-scene-chicago-pipeline-e-newsletter/'&gt;&lt;img src='/images/OTLradio-2.jpeg' alt='Outside the Loop Radio' title='Outside the Loop Radio' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Jan 5, 2012 &amp;#8211; Earlier is week the Chicago Lobbyists team did an interview with Mike Stephen from &lt;a href='http://www.outsidetheloopradio.com/2012/01/05/otl-episode-276-chicagolobbyists-org-discussing-the-local-comedy-scene-chicago-pipeline-e-newsletter/'&gt;Outside the Loop Radio&lt;/a&gt; on &lt;a href='http://wluw.org/'&gt;88.7 &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;WLUW&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.outsidetheloopradio.com/podpress_trac/web/686/0/otl-ep276-120105.mp3'&gt;Download the full interview&lt;/a&gt; or take a listen here (starts at around 3min in):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;audio controls=&quot;controls&quot;&gt;
&lt;source src=&quot;http://www.outsidetheloopradio.com/podpress_trac/web/686/0/otl-ep276-120105.mp3&quot; type=&quot;audio/mpeg&quot; /&gt;
Your browser does not support the audio element.
&lt;/audio&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
Doing the interview were Paul Baker, Derek Eder and Chad Pry. We discussed the origins of the project, the value it adds to Chicago citizens, surprises we found while going through the data, and our plans for the future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Make sure to check out &lt;a href='http://www.outsidetheloopradio.com'&gt;Outside the Loop Radio&lt;/a&gt; with Mike Stephen every Thursday at 10am on 88.7 &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;WLUW&lt;/span&gt;. Thanks again to Mike for the opportunity to share our work!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://wluw.org/'&gt;&lt;img src='/images/wluw88.gif' alt='88.7 WLUW' title='88.7 WLUW' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/28/govfresh-awards</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/28/govfresh-awards/"/>
    <title>In GovFresh competition, Chicago Lobbyists wins a first prize and Chicago places second as City of the Year</title>
    <updated>2011-12-28T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Paul Baker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class='r'&gt;&lt;a href='http://govfresh.com/2011/12/2011-govfresh-awards-winners/'&gt;&lt;img src='/images/2011-govfresh-awards.png' alt='2011 govfresh awards' title='2011 govfresh awards' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dec 28, 2011 &amp;#8211; On December 20, &lt;a href='http://govfresh.com/'&gt;GovFresh&lt;/a&gt; announced the &lt;a href='http://govfresh.com/2011/12/2011-govfresh-awards-winners/'&gt;winners of the 2011 GovFresh Awards&lt;/a&gt;. The website aims to encourage government-citizen collaboration in order to &amp;#8220;build a more engaged democracy.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='clear'&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Chicago Lobbyists placed first as &amp;#8220;Best use of open source&amp;#8221; and the city of Chicago placed second to New York City as &lt;a href='http://govfresh.com/2011/12/2011-govfresh-city-of-the-year-new-york-city/'&gt;City of the Year&lt;/a&gt;. New York was cited for its Engage &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;NYC&lt;/span&gt; initiative, aimed at getting designers and developers civically active, and &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;NYC&lt;/span&gt; Open Data, a repository of more than 850 city datasets, including public school data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were happy to see tweets from &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/ChicagosMayor/status/149194960275636224'&gt;Mayor Emmanuel&amp;#8217;s office&lt;/a&gt;, city &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/ChicagoCDO/status/149197667820503040'&gt;Chicago &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CDO&lt;/span&gt; Brett Goldstein&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/PoliticalEditor/status/149191489426169856'&gt;Mike Flannery&lt;/a&gt; at Fox News and OpenGov activist &lt;a href=''&gt;Steve Vance&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/ChicagosMayor/status/149194960275636224'&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc; &quot; src='/images/mayor-gf2011-tweet.png' alt='Tweet from the Mayors Office' title='Tweet from the Mayors Office' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We were also happy to see Chicago Lobbyists being used by journalists for online research, as in this New York Times &lt;a href='http://campaignstops.blogs.nytimes.com/2011/12/18/the-trouble-with-that-revolving-door/'&gt;article on lobbying&lt;/a&gt;. See the link to lobbying firm &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/firms/dla-piper-rudnick-gray-cary'&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;DLA&lt;/span&gt; Piper&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;GovFresh also highlights five Cook County open data visualizations based on the county&amp;#8217;s new &lt;a href='http://govfresh.com/2011/12/five-open-data-visualizations-from-cook-county-il/'&gt;Socrata open data catalog&lt;/a&gt;, including Public facilities and services, top sheriff&amp;#8217;s violations, outpatient registrations, mortgages, and elected officials.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/16/chicago-lobbyist-places-13th-in-a4mc</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/16/chicago-lobbyist-places-13th-in-a4mc/"/>
    <title>Chicago Lobbyists Places 13th in A4MC Grand Challenge Contest</title>
    <updated>2011-12-16T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Derek Eder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dec 16, 2011 &amp;#8211; The winners of the &lt;a href='http://appsformetrochicago.com/'&gt;Apps for Metro Chicago&lt;/a&gt; Grand Challenge were announced today at Excelerate Labs in Chicago. Chicago Lobbyists placed 13th out of 20.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc; &quot; src='/images/a4mc-cert.jpg' alt='Chicago Lobbyists 13th Place Certificate' title='Chicago Lobbyists 13th Place Certificate' /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Curiously, our award was given to us unsigned by &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;MCIC&lt;/span&gt; President Virginia Carlson. &lt;a href='http://mcic3.mcfol.org/'&gt;&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;MCIC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, or Metro Chicago Information Center, is the organization that runs Apps for Metro Chicago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The overall winner was &lt;a href='http://spothero.com/'&gt;SpotHero&lt;/a&gt;, a website that connects parking demand to parking supply by allowing parking spot owners to earn income by renting their spot when it&amp;#8217;s unoccupied. Congrats to them and all the other winners!&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/15/our-response-to-chicagos-lobbyist-rfp</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/15/our-response-to-chicagos-lobbyist-rfp/"/>
    <title>Our Response to Chicago's RFP for a Lobbyist Registration System</title>
    <updated>2011-12-15T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Derek Eder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dec 15, 2011 &amp;#8211; The City of Chicago put out a &lt;a href='/docs/Spec101998.pdf'&gt;Request for Proposals (&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/a&gt; to create an online lobbyist registration system. This &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt; stems directly from an &lt;a href='http://blogs.wttw.com/moreonthestory/2011/07/28/city-council-passes-ethics-reform-ordinance/'&gt;ethics ordinance&lt;/a&gt; passed on July 28th 2011.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='/docs/Spec101998.pdf'&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc; &quot; src='/images/RFP-cover.png' alt='City of Chicago Lobbyist Disclosure System RFP' title='City of Chicago Lobbyist Disclosure System RFP' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The RFP&amp;#8217;s objectives are for an outside contractor to build a system that will&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;enable lobbyists registered with the City to file, on line, all required registration documents and activity reports.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;enable the Department to review and approve these filings as quickly as possible and communicate with lobbyists who must and have not completed their filing requirements.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;make data compiled from all lobbyists&amp;#8217; filings publicly available on line in various searchable, queriable reporting formats.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Because of the work we have already done, and our goal to help bring openness and transparency to the City of Chicago, the people who created Chicago Lobbyists have decided to respond to this &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The challenge&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Responding to an &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt; for the City of Chicago is a herculean task. In the 152 pages, in addition to the usual cover letter, cost proposal, timeframe, etc, the responder must provide&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;a project management/implementation plan (including org chart, all software and third party products used, etc)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;audited financial statements for the past 3 years&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;an economic disclosure statement and affidavit (&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;EDS&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;proof of $500k workers compensation and employers liability&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;proof $2 million in professional liability insurance&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, this approach to an &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt; results in proposals from one type of contractor: firms that are very large and able to jump through all the hoops that the City has to ensure the minimum amount of risk and liability for the City itself. The idea is, if they remove all apparent risk in the selection process, no one will be to blame if the project fails since they vetted the options so thoroughly. What the contractor actually builds and how they plan on going about it is completely secondary. This type of process rarely provides high quality products at a reasonable price, especially in software development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a group of volunteers working in our free time on this project, we are not what this &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt; is targeting. We are, however, very competent developers and designers and have become experts on this lobbying data and how to display it. If the third objective of the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt; (above) sounds familiar to you, that&amp;#8217;s because you&amp;#8217;ve been to &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org'&gt;ChicagoLobbyists.org&lt;/a&gt;. We have already met objective 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Our proposal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Despite not being able to fulfill most of the requirements of the &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;RFP&lt;/span&gt;, we went ahead and responded anyway. We expect the city to pick one of their usual contractors, but hope that they will consider us as additional consultants for the design and front end development.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;&lt;a href='/docs/ChicagoLobbyistsProposal.pdf'&gt;Download our proposal&lt;/a&gt; (&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;PDF&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='/docs/ChicagoLobbyistsProposal.pdf'&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc; &quot; src='/images/RFP-response-packet.jpg' alt='Chicago Lobbyists RFP response' title='Chicago Lobbyists RFP response' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the proposal, besides showcasing the work we have already done, we offer to do the following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Design research, initially involving interviews with lobbyists entering the data, with the public that views data visualizations, and with city personnel charged with carrying out the ordinance&lt;/li&gt; 
	&lt;li&gt;User interface design and &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt;/&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CSS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/li&gt; 
	&lt;li&gt;Usability testing&lt;/li&gt; 
	&lt;li&gt;Web strategy&lt;/li&gt; 
	&lt;li&gt;Adapting ChicagoLobbyist.org design and code under a new city-controlled &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;URL&lt;/span&gt; to fulfill the public facing website requirement&lt;/li&gt; 
	&lt;li&gt;Creating an interoperable &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;API&lt;/span&gt; for exporting data in a normalized format&lt;/li&gt; 
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also advocate releasing as much code and design as possible as open source:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;We suggest that, whenever possible, the code, data schemas, and designs should be released as open source. Chicago has a unique opportunity to set an open standard for lobbying data structure, collection, and display—so other municipalities can use it. This will also set a good example for government-related projects that it makes sense to share.&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;br /&gt;
Moving from proprietary systems to open source makes collaboration and sharing easier and gives access to a wider pool of highly skilled talent. Examples of successful projects include Open 311, which the city plans to implement in 2012, and Open Street Maps, a viable alternative to Google and Bing Maps.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will have more updates the next few days. For more background information on government procurement, check out this informative article on The Information Diet: &lt;a href='http://www.informationdiet.com/blog/read/procurement-is-americas-big-problem'&gt;Procurement is America&amp;#8217;s Big Problem&lt;/a&gt; and CivicCommons&amp;#8217; wiki on &lt;a href='http://wiki.civiccommons.org/Legal_and_Procurement_Issues_Guide'&gt;Legal and Procurement Issues&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/14/chicago-lobbyists-a4mc-finalist</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/14/chicago-lobbyists-a4mc-finalist/"/>
    <title>We are a finalist in Apps for Metro Chicago</title>
    <updated>2011-12-14T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Derek Eder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dec 14, 2011 &amp;#8211; Last night, &lt;a href='http://appsformetrochicago.com/'&gt;Apps For Metro Chicago&lt;/a&gt; announced the 20 finalists for their Grand Challenge and Chicago Lobbyists was one of them!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The winners will be announced on Dec 16 at 10:30am. The Grand Challenge winner will be awarded $10,000. &lt;a href='http://appsformetrochicago.com/rules#prizes'&gt;More on the awards here&lt;/a&gt;. Good luck to everyone!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Judges&amp;#8217; Picks (5)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org'&gt;Chicago Lobbyists&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; Chicago Lobbyists is a web based app that is an open data, open government, and open source project intended to improve the transparency of interactions between the City of Chicago and lobbyists and their clients.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.allschedulesapp.com/'&gt;allSchedules&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; AllSchedules gives you access to a huge collection of transit schedules, for different transport modes (bus, metro,train, tram ferry, etc.), in multiple cities around the world. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.owtsee.com/'&gt;OwtSee&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; OwtSee is an Android based and a web based application that presents information about the Chicago parks and community events in one convenient  place. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.spotholechicago.com/'&gt;Spot Hole&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; This app is a tool that improves the process of citizens reporting potholes and helps the city clarify and address those concerns.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.transitstopapp.com/CTATracker/'&gt;Transit Stop: &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt; Tracker&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; This mobile app gives you quick and easy access to bus and train (‘L’) arrival time estimates for every Chicago Transit Authority (&lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CTA&lt;/span&gt;) bus and train stop.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Public voting picks (5)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://taxisharechicago.com/'&gt;Taxi Share&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; Taxi Share is an application designed to increase efficiency, reduce CO2 emississions and cut down on already congested streets and highways.  The app allows users to find each other and share a cab to popular destinations around the city and to the major airports. &lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://crimealertchicago.org/'&gt;Crime Alert&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; Crime Alert is a cross-platform web application, resource page, blog, and &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;SMS&lt;/span&gt; service that serves to alert users of crime in their community and surrounding area as rapidly as possible user-inputted addresses, and heavily customizable filters so that users only receive information that they believe to be relevant to their lives.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://massup.us/'&gt;MassUp.us&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; is Chicago&amp;#8217;s &amp;quot;Social Cycling System. &amp;quot; It&amp;#8217;s a Web App comprehensively meeting the needs of urban bicyclists. It features maps, directions, compass, ride recording, calorie counter, speedometer, weather and much more.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://ghabit.com/'&gt;Make Green a Habit&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211;  This is a green social network with a simple goal: to inspire people and organizations to create a greener and sustainable habitat. Ghabit uses social media technology to allow users to create an online green community, track and compare green habits, and much more!&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://sites.google.com/site/rezmobileapps/treking'&gt;TreKing&lt;/a&gt; – The only Android app to support all four major transit systems in Chicago.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Winners carried over from previous rounds (10)&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Community Round&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://ifinditchicago.wordpress.com/'&gt;iFindit Chicago&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; An android app that is designed to help low income and homeless residents connect with critical resources such as medical clinics, food pantries, shelters etc.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://miparquelv.wordpress.com/'&gt;Mi Parque&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; is a bilingual participatory placemaking web and smartphone application that helps residents of the community contribute and share their vision for the future of Little Village’s new park. Community members can submit ideas about how to make this park, and other open spaces in the area, safer, greener and healthier places that meet community needs&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.cyberwalkabout.com/'&gt;Chicago Local Guide&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; is an android app is meant to help local people as well as tourists find:  interesting places and points-of-interest near them; locate specials and promotions from local businesses; updates on cultural, social, and technology events around Chicago; and breaking local news.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://www.okcopay.com/'&gt;OkCopay&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; A comparison search engine for medical care that allows users to search for the procedure they need, compare local providers, and view their actual prices.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://aqualab.cs.northwestern.edu/projects/Fixit.html'&gt;Fixit!&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; A mobile app that allows Chicagoans to report issues, like public property damages, that require city attention.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Transportation Round&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://spothero.com/'&gt;SpotHero&lt;/a&gt; -Spothero efficiently connects parking demand and parking supply.  We allow parking spot owners to earn income by renting their spot when it&amp;#8217;s unoccupied&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://faspark.com/market/'&gt;FasPark&lt;/a&gt; -Faspark helps drivers find street parking in real time.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://chicago.inthirty.com/'&gt;InThirty&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; Use InThirty to see the Chicago city resources that you can access within a thirty-minute train, bus, or walk.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='https://market.android.com/details?id=edu.northwestern.cs.aqualab.android.TrailBlazeChicago&amp;hl=en'&gt;TrailBlaze Chicago&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211; TrailBlaze Chicago records and anonymously reports your bicycle tracks, allowing you to vote for new paths simply by carrying your phone while you bike.&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href='http://itunes.apple.com/us/app/gochicago/id457501927?mt=8'&gt;GoChicago&lt;/a&gt; &amp;#8211;  With GoChicago, users can make a list of the places in Chicago they&amp;#8217;d like to see, view directions to each place on a map, or call the place for more information.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/02/chicago-lobbyists-v2-is-here</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/02/chicago-lobbyists-v2-is-here/"/>
    <title>Chicago Lobbyists Version 2 Is Here</title>
    <updated>2011-12-02T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Derek Eder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dec 2, 2011 &amp;#8211; We just rolled out a new version of Chicago Lobbyists last night. Thanks to our meetings with Chicago &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CDO&lt;/span&gt; &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/ChicagoCDO'&gt;Brett Goldstein&lt;/a&gt; and the efforts from his staff, we now have the ability to show:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;What clients paid to each lobbyist (and how much)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Which actions clients hired lobbyists to take&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;How much money each client spent (total) on lobbyists in 2010&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new data also seems to have been cleaned up and normalized quite a bit (we still had to do some normalizing ourselves &amp;#8211; especially with addresses), resulting in a more accurate picture of lobbying activity in Chicago for 2010.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is a rundown of the new features:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/clients'&gt;Most active clients&lt;/a&gt; is now determined by amount spent instead of number of lobbyists hired (&lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/clients/salvation-army'&gt;Salvation Army&lt;/a&gt;, you are now #1 with $380,000 spent on lobbyists in 2010)&lt;/p&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/clients'&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc; &quot; src='/images/v2-client-list.png' alt='New client listing' title='New client listing' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All detail pages have a summary section at the top, displaying total amounts, number of lobbyists, number of clients, number of firms, and number of actions (depending on what you&amp;#8217;re viewing). Here&amp;#8217;s an example of each:&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;ul&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Lobbyist &amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/lobbyists/ronald-johnson'&gt;Ronald Johnson&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Firm &amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/firms/neal-and-leroy-llc'&gt;Neal &amp;amp; Leroy, &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;LLC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Client &amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/clients/fifth-third-bank'&gt;Fifth Third Bank&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
		&lt;li&gt;Agency &amp;#8211; &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/agencies/city-council'&gt;City Council&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/lobbyists/ronald-johnson'&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc; &quot; src='/images/v2-lobbyist-detail.png' alt='Lobbyist detail - Ronald Johnson' title='Lobbyist detail - Ronald Johnson' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Global site search (using &lt;a href='http://www.google.com/cse/'&gt;Google custom search engine&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every lobbyist action has a client associated with it&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Every lobbyist payment shows the client who paid them&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;Categorized lobbyist expenditures (office expenses, food, travel, education, etc) are now listed&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;We cross referenced the City of Chicago &lt;a href='http://data.cityofchicago.org/Administration-Finance/Payments/s4vu-giwb'&gt;Payments database&lt;/a&gt;, and listed all payments by Chicago to each client (example: &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/clients/christy-webber-landscapes'&gt;Christy Webber Landscapes&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/clients/christy-webber-landscapes'&gt;&lt;img style=&quot;border: 1px solid #ccc; &quot; src='/images/v2-city-payments.png' alt='Christy Webber Landscapes - City Payments' title='Christy Webber Landscapes - City Payments' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;All detail pages now have tabs for each section so you can see all the rich data, without cluttering the page&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;&lt;p&gt;All data on the detail pages is sortable and searchable (thanks to jQuery &lt;a href='http://datatables.net/'&gt;Datatables&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;All detail pages have comments (powered by &lt;a href='http://disqus.com/dashboard/'&gt;Disqus&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re all really excited about these new updates. We now have the most accurate and detailed visualization of lobbyist activities around. That&amp;#8217;s something to be proud of.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/01/an-open-data-story</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/12/01/an-open-data-story/"/>
    <title>An Open Data Story</title>
    <updated>2011-12-01T00:00:00-06:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Paul Baker&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dec 1, 2011 &amp;#8211; In almost all open data projects, providing raw data is not enough. And it’s not enough to be a good programmer or designer. To be useful, we need to be able to figure out what questions the data might reveal and which of these might be useful for the public to know.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p class='r'&gt;&lt;a href='http://data.cityofchicago.org/Ethics/Lobbyist-Data-2010-Lobbyist-Registry/2ft4-4uik'&gt;&lt;img src='http://chicagolobbyists.org/images/city-data-portal.png' alt='Lobbyist Data - 2010 Lobbyist Registry' title='Lobbyist Data - 2010 Lobbyist Registry' /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In early July 2011, the City of Chicago released &lt;a href='http://data.cityofchicago.org/browse?tags=lobbyists'&gt;14 sets of lobbying-related data&lt;/a&gt;, including lobbyists, lobbying agencies, gifts to city employees, expenditures, clients of lobbyists, etc. However, an ordinary human being could not make heads or tails of this without some sort of integration. &lt;br /&gt;
That’s why we built &lt;a href='http://chicagoLobbyists.org'&gt;ChicagoLobbyists.org&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class='clear'&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Chicago Lobbyists v1.0&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we went through each data set, attempting to draw relationships among them by looking for common fields such as clients, lobbying firms, and individual lobbyists. Our goal was to reveal answers to questions such as, &amp;#8220;WalMart paid which lobbyist, with which lobbying firm, how much money, to argue on their behalf in front of which department or committee, and for what purpose?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We soon found out that we couldn’t answer that question. In the above example, we could show which lobbyists Walmart paid, which firm the lobbyist worked for, and which city agencies the lobbyist appeared before, but not which tasks lobbyists were hired to do for WalMart.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Meeting with the City&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After the July Google hackathon, at which we built and launched the site, we met with the city’s Chief Data Officer, &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/ChicagoCDO'&gt;Brett Goldstein&lt;/a&gt;, and some IT staff, and asked: &lt;br /&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a way to determine compensation that comes to a firm versus lobbyist? (We can’t be sure adding up compensation of all lobbyists within a firm is accurate.)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a way to determine how much a client paid to a lobbying firm or lobbyist?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Related to the question above, can we retrieve the purpose for a client payment?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Can we receive data before 2010? If so, what years are available?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a way to determine which client requested an action in front of an agency? We only know which lobbyist requested an action—see example: &lt;a href='http://chicagolobbyists.org/lobbyists/theodore-brunsvold'&gt;Theodore Brunsvold&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Are street addresses available for lobbying firms (some give political donations from many different addresses)?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Do you have a good state contact from which we could request political donation data?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a list of all city datasets available (besides those on Socrata)?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;br /&gt;
	&lt;li&gt;Is there a schedule of when particular datasets are updated (frequency, time period)?&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The City responds with updated data&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By late August, Brett’s team had collected and &lt;a href='http://www.cityofchicago.org/city/en/depts/mayor/press_room/press_releases/2011/august_2011/mayor_emanuel_announcesnewlobbyistdatathatprovidesclearconnectio.html'&gt;posted the data that we had requested&lt;/a&gt;. Now, we are able to incorporate the new data and change the site’s design to show more detailed and new views (&lt;strong&gt;these changes are coming in the next day or so &amp;#8211; stay tuned&lt;/strong&gt;). Now we can answer most of the important questions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Next steps &amp;hellip;&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Our next steps are to incorporate political donations to city officials by lobbyists and organizations. It would also be good to show how elected officials voted on issues of interest to lobbyists who have donated to them and their clients.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The entire &lt;a href='http://data.cityofchicago.org/Administration-Finance/Budget-2012-Budget-Recommendations-Appropriations/8dps-5d4x'&gt;2012 city budget&lt;/a&gt; is about $3 billion—all of it paid by residents. Fees paid to lobbyists to influence government decisions will probably be in the neighborhood of $13 million, or about .4% of $3 billion.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We’re the 99.6%. Lobbyists paid by organizations are .4%. Are lobbyists the tail that wags the dog?&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/08/19/opengov-chicago-presentation</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/08/19/opengov-chicago-presentation/"/>
    <title>Presentation at the OpenGov Chicago meetup</title>
    <updated>2011-08-19T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Derek Eder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Aug 19, 2011 &amp;#8211; Ryan Briones and Chad Pry &lt;a href='http://www.meetup.com/OpenGovChicago/events/28864281/'&gt;gave a presentation to the OpenGov Chicago meetup&lt;/a&gt; on the origin and future of ChicagoLobbyists.org. Below are the meeting notes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Origins&lt;/h3&gt; 
&lt;p&gt;Started with an existing Obtiva/Webitects relationship. Paul, Ryan, Chad and Derek were all interested in doing an opendata project. The Google Hack-a-thon presented an opportunity and put on pressure for us to really build something. The lobbyist data was just released the week before and knowing about lobbyist activity is considered to be a &amp;#8216;juicy&amp;#8217; topic.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;How did we do it?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each of the main contributors spent ~5 hours the week before the hack-a-thon cleaning up data with &lt;a href='http://code.google.com/p/google-refine/'&gt;Google Refine&lt;/a&gt;, eyeballing obvious relationships in the data, doing some base &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; layouts and setting up a host for the application (Ruby/Sinatra). At the Google Open Data Hack-a-thon 6 people worked on the project: the 4 originators plus Ruthie and Chirag. By the end of the day we had a basic structure and database set up. The following weeks, we worked in our spare time and now have a minimum viable product.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;What is in the future?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Add more meaningful data to inform you about lobbyists, clients and agencies. We have started a relationship working with Brett Goldstein (Chicago&amp;#8217;s Chief Data Officer) and the Ethics department to fill in the gaps. Once we have Chicago down, we will generalize our model for use with other cities to visualize their lobbyist data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All the code is open source and can be &lt;a href='https://github.com/chicago-lobbyists/web'&gt;checked out on Github&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <id>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/07/17/origin-story-chicago-open-data-hackathon</id>
    <link type="text/html" rel="alternate" href="http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/2011/07/17/origin-story-chicago-open-data-hackathon/"/>
    <title>Origin Story - Chicago Open Data Hackathon</title>
    <updated>2011-07-17T00:00:00-05:00</updated>
    <author>
      <name>Chicago Lobbyists</name>
      <uri>http://blog.chicagolobbyists.org/</uri>
    </author>
    <content type="html">&lt;p&gt;by Derek Eder&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;July 17, 2011 &amp;#8211; Chicago Lobbyists started as an existing relationship between civic-minded members of &lt;a href='http://obtiva.com/'&gt;Obtiva&lt;/a&gt; and &lt;a href='http://webitects.com'&gt;Webitects&lt;/a&gt;. In early July 2011, when Google announced it would be hosting a hackathon focused on Chicago civic data, it was a perfect excuse to bring our group together for the first time to build something great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Paul pointed out that the &lt;a href='http://data.cityofchicago.org/browse?tags=lobbyists'&gt;lobbyist data&lt;/a&gt; was particularly interesting. It was always a hot topic in the media and the City had just released it a few weeks prior and we all quickly agreed to focus on that for our hackathon project. The question then was, what could we do with it?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The week before the hackathon, we brainstormed over this very question and came up with the idea that it could be a &amp;#8216;Facebook for lobbyists&amp;#8217;. Each lobbyist would have a page, which would show various details about their firms, the money they were paid, and the actions they sought in front of city agencies (City Council, Department of Buildings, etc). From there, other page layouts emerged, and going in to the Saturday hackathon, the team had developed &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;HTML&lt;/span&gt; templates for those very pages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The day of the hackathon, our group worked for 8 hours straight parsing the data, building out the Ruby/Sinatra app and developing additional pages. Along the way, they got some help from &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/patelc75'&gt;Chirag Patel&lt;/a&gt; on the database setup and &lt;a href='https://twitter.com/#!/unruthless'&gt;Ruthie BenDor&lt;/a&gt; on the front-end development. By the end of the day, we had a partially working home page, which we presented to the other hackathon attendees (see photos below) to great fanfare.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Running with that momentum, we continued to develop the site over the next few weeks. By August 3rd, we had a &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;MVP&lt;/span&gt; (minimum viable product).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Slideshow from the Chicago Open Data Hackathon on July 17th 2011 courtesy of Chicago &lt;span class=&quot;caps&quot;&gt;CTO&lt;/span&gt; John Tolva.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;iframe align=&quot;center&quot; src=&quot;http://www.flickr.com/slideShow/index.gne?group_id=&amp;user_id=68506146@N00&amp;set_id=72157627083380801/with/5944894188&amp;text=&quot; frameBorder=&quot;0&quot; width=&quot;500&quot; height=&quot;450&quot; scrolling=&quot;no&quot;&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</content>
  </entry>
  
 
</feed>